<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Clintonville Neighborhood Greenways</title>
 <link href="http://clintonvillegreenways.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://clintonvillegreenways.org"/>
 <updated>2022-02-25T18:04:29-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://clintonvillegreenways.org/atom.xml</id>
 <author>
   <name>Will Koehler</name>
   <uri>http://clintonvillegreenways.org</uri>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Shared Use Paths Connect Neighborhoods Throughout Columbus</title>
   <link href="http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2022/02/20/shared-use-paths-connect-neighborhoods-throughout-columbus.html"/>
   <published>2022-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</published>
   <updated>2022-02-20T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2022/02/20/shared-use-paths-connect-neighborhoods-throughout-columbus</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A component of the Clintonville Neighborhood Greenway is a shared use path that connects
Rathbone Ave to Jeffrey Place. The path will be constructed on city parkland. Here’s a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/d/u/0/viewer?mid=1hsT6lhfuUlh2AUk1Lp9lDTgUFNs&amp;amp;ll=40.06238694099186%2C-83.02532179556246&amp;amp;z=17&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; of the location and here’s a
&lt;a href=&quot;/images/connectors/rathbone-jeffrey-place-connector.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;drawing&lt;/a&gt;
of what it will look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this may seem unusual, shared use paths are used throughout Columbus to connect
neighborhoods to each other and to nearby trail systems. These connections make the neighborhoods
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brucefreemanrailtrail.org/pdf/LA-Metro-Bike-paths-safety-property-values.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
safer and more desireable to live in.
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neighborhoods are safer because there are more “eyes on the street”. More
people that live in the neighborhood are out and about and are more likely to see
and report suspcicious activity. The neighborhoods are more desireable because people
have more options to move safely around their community. They have more “random
encounters” with other people, resulting in increased feelings of belonging and
wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;height:1em&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;boathouse-drive-to-astral-drive&quot;&gt;Boathouse Drive to Astral Drive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This short connector links two neighborhoods in Northwest Columbus.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.0474495,-83.1164041,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;See it on a map&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Approaching from the North&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/boathouse-drive-neighborhood-connector-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Approaching from the South&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/boathouse-drive-neighborhood-connector-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;height:1em&quot;&gt;&lt;!--SPACER--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lincoln-ave-to-vinewood-drive-i71-overpass&quot;&gt;Lincoln Ave to Vinewood Drive I71 Overpass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This I71 overpass provides a vital connection between Salem Village and
Forest Park in Northest Columbus.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.0757375,-82.9877547,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;See it on a map&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Approaching from the West&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/lincoln-ave-i71-overpass-neighborhood-connector-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Approaching from the East&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/lincoln-ave-i71-overpass-neighborhood-connector-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;height:1em&quot;&gt;&lt;!--SPACER--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alum-creek-trail-connections&quot;&gt;Alum Creek Trail Connections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous connections between neighborhoods and the Alum creek trail. Some
are shown below. These connections provide a safe way for people in nearby homes to
get onto the trail without using a busy road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Southridge Drive
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.0409583,-82.9393895,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(map)&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/alum-creek-trail-system-southridge-drive-connector.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Westerville Crossing Drive
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.0867574,-82.9254604,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(map)&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/alum-creek-trail-system-westerville-crossing-drive-connector.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;height:1em&quot;&gt;&lt;!--SPACER--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worthington-estates-to-olentangy-trail&quot;&gt;Worthington Estates to Olentangy Trail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worthington Estates is connected to the Olentangy Trail in 4 locations (three are shown below).
These connection provide a safe way for people in Worthington Estates to get onto the
Olentangy Trail system.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.0994204,-83.0329385,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;See it on a map&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Worthington Estates to Olentangy Trail Connections&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/worthington-estates-olentangy-trail-connector-map.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/worthington-estates-olentangy-trail-connector-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/worthington-estates-olentangy-trail-connector-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/worthington-estates-olentangy-trail-connector-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;height:1em&quot;&gt;&lt;!--SPACER--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dublin-neighborhood-connections&quot;&gt;Dublin Neighborhood Connections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dublin neighborhoods are connected with a large network of shared use paths.
These connections, most of which pass directly between homes, provide a safe
way for residents of Dublin to move around their neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Shared use path connections in Dublin, OH
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.1393509,-83.1353357,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(see it on a map)&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-map-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Shared use path connections in Dublin, OH
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.1498429,-83.1438725,17z/data=!5m1!1e3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(see it on a map)&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-map-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Glenfinnan Court&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hawthornden Court&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Turnberry Court&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Aryshire Drive&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fit rounded&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Aryshire Drive&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/connectors/dublin-oh-trail-system-neighborhood-connector-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Winter 2016 Progress Update</title>
   <link href="http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2016/01/08/winter-2016-progress-update.html"/>
   <published>2016-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published>
   <updated>2016-01-08T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2016/01/08/winter-2016-progress-update</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve met several times with the city over the last 6 months to discuss the Neighborhood Greenways
route and design. While many of the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/08/phase-1-route-and-design.html&quot;&gt;design recommendations we made for phase 1&lt;/a&gt;
may seem simple (such as painting green-backed sharrows on the road), they require exemptions from
the strict rules that determine what types of pavement markings and signs can be used on public roads.
However, to achieve the safety level of a true neighborhood greenway, we need to use the
latest design elements. Many other cities are already constructing street networks using these newer
design elements. If we don’t match their innovations in Columbus, we risk getting left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, the city understands the importance of building a safe neighborhood greenway network.
By incorporating advice from the city bike coordinator and local advocates, the city is looking for
ways to improve on designs that they’ve used in the past. The goal is to make Clintonville Neighborhood
Greenways a model street network that will serve as a template for neighborhoods throughout Columbus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-our-volunteer-teams&quot;&gt;Join our volunteer teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, we’re creating teams to take on specific tasks as we move closer to
building the greenways. In the months to come, we’ll be working on outreach to Clintonville
residents, businesses, schools, and other interested parties to get the word out about the
coming neighborhood greenways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are creating teams for&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branding and marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community outreach&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grants and fundraising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legal and Business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in pitching in as a volunteer, please sign up here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/17w5HG4pIi6R9qV0zsFzMHERkVXj2713ZYTg59iF8q6Y/viewform?usp=send_form&quot;&gt;Clintonville Neighborhood Greenway Signup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;were-working-towards-501c3-status&quot;&gt;We’re working towards 501(c)(3) status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our application for 501(c)(3) status is coming along. Status as a tax-exempt organization
will make advocacy and raising money easier. We’re fortunate to already have several experienced
grant writers who will be helping us raise money to further our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Phase 1 Route and Design</title>
   <link href="http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2015/05/08/phase-1-route-and-design.html"/>
   <published>2015-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</published>
   <updated>2015-09-11T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2015/05/08/phase-1-route-and-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Phase 1 of the Clintonville Neighborhood Greenways has been funded! We are in the process
of working on a detailed route and design with the City of Columbus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a working document outlining our recommendations for Phase 1 of the Clintonville
Neighborhood Greenways. It’s intended to be a starting point for the detailed designs that
will be developed by the City of Columbus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategy&quot;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our strategy for building the Neighborhood Greenways is to start with the minimal
infrastructure that achieves our design goals (known in the tech world as a “minimal
viable product”). We will then monitor the success of the Neighborhood Greenways and
evolve and improve the design as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, the minimal viable product is a network of neighborhood roads that feel safe for
all ages and abilities. This boils down to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Traffic speed under 25mph&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Traffic volume less than 1000 cars/day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People feel relaxed and safe biking and walking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these metrics can be measured, recorded, and tracked over time. If we meet our goals, no
additional treatments are needed. If we don’t meet our goals then additional treatments can
be considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-design-guidelines&quot;&gt;General Design Guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighborhood greenways consist of the following elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A distinctive look&lt;/strong&gt; so that all road users are aware of the neighborhood greenway.
People driving are alerted that the street is prioritized for biking and walking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treatments to reduce vehicle speed and volume as needed.&lt;/strong&gt; The goal is to keep speed
under 25mph and ADT under 1000 cars per day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved treatments at busy intersections&lt;/strong&gt; to help people biking and walking cross more easily.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free-flow travel for people biking and walking&lt;/strong&gt; by assigning the right-of-way to the
neighborhood greenway at intersections wherever possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Way-finding signs&lt;/strong&gt; guiding people along the route and letting them know what is
nearby, for example parks, schools, and local businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;route-and-design-recommendations&quot;&gt;Route and design recommendations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Phase 1 route was chosen to connect to all parts of Clintonville while remaining easy to
implement. Wherever possible, we chose streets that already met our goals for Neighborhood
Greenways so that minimal changes will be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;map_container full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a class=&quot;overlay&quot; href=&quot;https://mapsengine.google.com/maps/d/viewer?mid=zEAPhiHiDgA8.kIVN6G1UPcLo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://mapsengine.google.com/map/u/0/embed?mid=zEAPhiHiDgA8.kIVN6G1UPcLo&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;calumet-street&quot;&gt;Calumet Street&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calumet Street &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘A’ on map)&lt;/span&gt; is the biggest challenge on the
Neighborhood Greenways route. Traffic volume is 2200 cars/day - twice what we would like. 85th
percentile speed is 33mph in some places - well above our goal of 25mph. Because of the windy
nature of the road and higher traffic volumes, unsafe passes are common, making this road
unsuitable in it’s current condition for families and other risk-averse people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calumet is a neighborhood collector, which means traffic restrictions will be difficult. Because
on-street parking is widely used, especially south of Weber, we cannot make room for bike lanes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Visually narrow road.&lt;/b&gt; The wider sections of Calumet lead to faster speeds. One option
is to stripe out an 8’ parking lane. Also evaluate for green infrastructure such as curb bump
outs in coordination with Columbus Blueprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Remove yellow center line.&lt;/b&gt; A yellow center line encourages higher speeds and more
dangerous passing behavior. Use short sections of yellow center lines only at major intersections
(Arcadia, Weber, Broadway) and around blind curves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Use more frequent sharrows.&lt;/b&gt; More frequent sharrows are advised for roads with higher
traffic volume and speed. Consider sharrows at 75 to 100 foot intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Add “Bikes may use full lane” signs.&lt;/b&gt; These signs are the recommended standard for
clarifying that bikes are allowed full use of the road. “Share the road” signs should not
be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/calumet.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersection-of-torrence-road-and-high-street&quot;&gt;Intersection of Torrence Road and High Street&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic at this intersection &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘B’ on map)&lt;/span&gt; increased
significantly after the new Starbucks opened. Although drivers are fairly cautious and aware
of people biking and walking, the large volume of cars can make navigating this intersection
tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Add ladder-style crosswalks&lt;/b&gt;. More prominent crosswalks will highlight the Neighborhood
Greenways crossing, raise awareness of the increased bike and pedestrian traffic, and make
people walking and biking feel more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersection-of-milton-northmoor-and-montrose-way&quot;&gt;Intersection of Milton, Northmoor, and Montrose Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 6-way intersection &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘C’ on map)&lt;/span&gt; is large and has numerous
conflict points. While traffic volume is generally low, it can still be tricky to navigate with bikes,
cars and pedestrians all using the same space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Add a planted traffic circle.&lt;/b&gt; Traffic entering the circle yields to traffic that’s already in
the circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/six-way.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersection-of-milton-and-hollenback&quot;&gt;Intersection of Milton and Hollenback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intersection &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘D’ on map)&lt;/span&gt; is difficult to navigate because
it’s offset with the exit from the library. Traffic is generally slow and people navigate cautiously.
The most common conflict is between people turning left from Milton onto Hollenback and people exiting
the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long-term this intersection should be re-aligned with the library exit and converted to a 4-way stop.
For Phase 1 &lt;b&gt;consider adding additional sharrows through the turn&lt;/b&gt; to highlight the presence of bikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/intersection-of-milton-and-hollenback.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hollenback&quot;&gt;Hollenback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollenback &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘E’ on map)&lt;/span&gt; is a park road. Traffic volume is sometimes
high, especially on evenings with children’s soccer. However speeds are low and people are alert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a side path that parallels Hollenback. This path is narrow and the surface is
uneven. There are several conflict points where the path crosses driveways. Getting on and
off the path also requires crossing traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some people may choose to use the side path, the Neighborhood Greenways route should use
Hollenback and should be marked with sharrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/hollenback-road.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter-house-parking-lot&quot;&gt;Shelter house parking lot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The route past the shelter house parking lot &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘F’ on map)&lt;/span&gt;
is confusing. It appears the road goes straight into the parking lot. There are two parking
lot exits with stop signs, but because of the curvy nature of the road, it’s not clear who has
the right of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Use sharrows and a white edge line to define the travel lane.&lt;/b&gt; Add stop bars at parking
lot exits to clarify right of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/shelter-house-parking-lot.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exit-to-olentangy-blvd&quot;&gt;Exit to Olentangy Blvd&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace gate with bollards, allowing people biking to pass through, or add a new bike
exit following the desired direction of travel &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘G’ on map)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/exit-to-olentangy.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersection-of-olentangy-blvd-and-henderson-road&quot;&gt;Intersection of Olentangy Blvd and Henderson Road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light cycle at this intersection &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘H’ on map)&lt;/span&gt; is very long.
This adds significant delay to trips on the Neighborhood Greenways route. It also causes a large
number of cars to queue up on Olentangy Blvd during rush hour. &lt;b&gt;Evaluate shortening the light
cycle&lt;/b&gt; to reduce delay for Neighborhood Greenways traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a problem with drivers bullying people on bikes at this intersection. Drivers that
want to turn right don’t like waiting behind bikes that are going straight and sometimes honk
and yell at them to “get out of the road”. Bikes often go up on the sidewalk ramps to wait
which causes problems at they re-integrate into the traffic flow when the light changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Evaluate the intersection for bike boxes&lt;/b&gt;. Bike boxes would create space for bikes
and would clearly communicate that people on bikes should wait in the road and not on the
sidewalk ramps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Add ladder-style crosswalks&lt;/b&gt;. More prominent crosswalks will highlight the Neighborhood
Greenways crossing, raise awareness of the increased bike and pedestrian traffic, and make
people walking and biking feel more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;weisheimer&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersection-of-weisheimer-road-and-high-street&quot;&gt;Intersection of Weisheimer Road and High Street&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intersection is offset &lt;span class=&quot;muted smaller&quot;&gt;(‘I’ on map)&lt;/span&gt;. However, since there
is a 4-way traffic signal, it would be possible to &lt;b&gt;re-align the intersection for bikes&lt;/b&gt;. This
could be done by converting one of the bank exit lanes to a two-way bike lane, or by adding a two-way
bike lane to the north of the bank exit. The north-east corner of Weisheimer and High is being
redeveloped, so this is a perfect opportunity to start the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second option would be to &lt;b&gt;improve the sidewalk on the east side of High Street&lt;/b&gt; and route
bikes along the sidewalk in front of the business. This creates a conflict point with cars
turning from High Street onto E. Weisheimer Road. The conflict could be eliminated with a choker
entrance preventing turns onto E. Weisheimer Rd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In either case &lt;b&gt;add ladder-style crosswalks&lt;/b&gt;. More prominent crosswalks will highlight the Neighborhood
Greenway crossing and make people walking and biking feel more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/intersection-of-weisheimer-and-high.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;road-markings-and-street-signs&quot;&gt;Road markings and street signs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;road-markings&quot;&gt;Road markings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sharrow&lt;/b&gt; - use throughout the greenway to mark roads as shared use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Way-marking sharrow&lt;/b&gt; - use to indicate left or right turn ahead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Green sharrow&lt;/b&gt; - use on roads with higher volume to emphasize shared use lanes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gateway sharrow&lt;/b&gt; - use one gateway sharrow after each major intersection to alert road
users to the presence of the Neighborhood Greenways.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sharrow flower&lt;/b&gt; - use to mark intersections of Neighborhood Greenways routes to alert
people that they have a choice to make.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/road-markings.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;street-signs-and-way-finding-signs&quot;&gt;Street signs and way-finding signs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branded street signs and way-finding signs add awareness of the Neighborhood Greenways route.
Examples of neighborhood greenway street signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/street-signs.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of neighborhood greenway way-finding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/phase-1/way-finding-signs.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;traffic-volume-targets&quot;&gt;Traffic volume targets&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on guidance from engineers in Portland, we feel that targeting traffic volumes of under
1000 cars/day is essential to making a neighborhood greenway safe enough for all ages
and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the guidelines that Portland is proposing to become official policy for their
neighborhood greenways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1,000 autos per day is the desired maximum.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1,500+ autos per day is acceptable, but diversion is considered on a case by case basis and
recommended if there is an expectation that other changes, or the greenway’s location, will attract
significant traffic to the project street.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More than 2,000 autos per day necessitates diversion in some form if the neighborhood greenway
street is to be a shared space with auto traffic. This is primarily because Portland has a desired
maximum speed of 20 mph, and state law permits us to reduce the residential statutory speed of 25
mph by 5 mph on greenway streets, but only if the residential street has less than 2,000 autos per day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance is based in part on research documented in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://transweb.sjsu.edu/PDFs/research/1005-low-stress-bicycling-network-connectivity.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Low-Stress Bicycling and Network Connectivity&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;muted&quot; style=&quot;font-size:80%&quot;&gt;(PDF 2.4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-cities-design-guidelines&quot;&gt;Other cities’ design guidelines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portland OR and Berkeley CA both have successful neighborhood greenway networks. For reference
their neighborhood greenway design guidelines are linked below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portland, OR&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pdx.edu/ibpi/sites/www.pdx.edu.ibpi/files/BicycleBoulevardGuidebook%28optimized%29.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fundamentals of Bicycle Boulevard Planning &amp;amp; Design&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;muted&quot; style=&quot;font-size:80%&quot;&gt;(PDF 5.2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Berkeley, CA&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cityofberkeley.info/Public_Works/Transportation/Bicycle_Boulevard_Guidelines.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bicycle Boulevard Design Tools and Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Edit:&lt;/b&gt; This post was updated on 9/11/2015 to align with current best practices and
feedback from the city.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New Bike Parking in Clintonville</title>
   <link href="http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2015/05/04/new-bike-parking-in-clintonville.html"/>
   <published>2015-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</published>
   <updated>2015-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://clintonvillegreenways.org/2015/05/04/new-bike-parking-in-clintonville</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the major obstacles to a more bike-infused lifestyle is a lack of designated parking near
restaurants, stores, salons, and other favorite businesses. Leaving your bike chained to a parking
meter, tree, or fence is risky (not to mention, unsightly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designated bike parking gives people a safe and convenient place to park their bike. Because bike racks
take up little space, people can ride right up to the front door and have a safe place to lock up their
bicycles. This encourages more people to bike which reduces traffic congestion and parking hassles for
people that arrive by car. Everyone benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full rounded shadow&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bike-parking/bike-parking-in-clintonville.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Clintonville Neighborhood Greenways is working with local businesses and the City of Columbus to add
more bike parking in Clintonville. We are sending volunteers to local businesses to show them how
easy it is to request a free bike rack from the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you run a business in Clintonville and we haven’t visited you yet, requesting a free bike rack
from the city is easy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Call the City of Columbus (614)645-3111 and request a bicycle rack&lt;/b&gt;. They will ask you for
the address where you are requesting to have a rack installed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Infrastructure Management will follow-up on your request&lt;/b&gt;. Check your mail and phone messages for
any possible follow-up questions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notify the owner of the property at the address where you are requesting a rack.&lt;/b&gt; They may need to
approve the request before Infrastructure Management can proceed with the installation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Welcome customers on bikes to park in front of your business!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a question about how bike parking can improve your business and make our neighborhood more livable?
Contact us at: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hello@clintonvillegreenways.org?subject=Question about Bike Parking in Clintonville&quot;&gt;hello@clintonvillegreenways.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>